What if fish oil were changing your
arteries? Well, it's not even a question
because there are multiple studies
indicating that to be the case.
Technically, it's not limited to fish
oil, but to really any omega-3 fat
supplement or just omega-3s as a whole.
While we've gone over the ways that
omega-3 fats affect our heart, we've
never gone into how they affect our
arteries. Specifically, the plaque in
your arteries change when you consume
omega-3s. According to an array of
studies, we know that atherosclerosis,
so the plaque that develops in your
arteries, are a major cause of heart
attack, stroke, and much more directly
and indirectly. But the issue is far
more complex because the quality or type
of plaque makes a massive difference on
your risk. For example, soft plaque,
also known as non-calcified plaque, is
especially dangerous because it's
susceptible to rupturing and lodging in
finer blood vessels. stopping blood flow
to downstream areas, killing those
areas. On the other hand, calcified or
even fibrodic plaque is less dangerous
because it's considered stable or
semi-stable, meaning it generally has a
cap on the top of the soft plaque that
protects from erupting into the
bloodstream. To be clear, it's still not
ideal, but between the two, it's
preferred. So, what happens to this
plaque when we consume omega-3s, fish
oil, or otherwise? In this study, the
researchers are using non-invasive
imaging called CT angography to measure
the plaque within the arteries of two
groups of people. One group consuming
omega-3s, and the other was not
supplementing the control group. As seen
by these data, the left is the control
group, so the non-supplementers, and the
right are the omega-3 group. This
measurement is of houndsfield units,
meaning the higher it goes, the more
fibrous and possibly calcified the
plaque is. Generally, values reaching
100 and above indicate more fibrous
plaque, and values into the higher
hundreds and even thousands indicate
calcified plaque. So, knowing what we
know about plaque, we can clearly see
that the omega-3 condition is reaching
into those higher thresholds, indicating
more solid fibroic plaque. Similarly, if
we look at another metric Gcore, which
tells us on a scale the type of plaque
burden, it looks like this. Notice the
blood vessel. Then notice the four cate
categorization. So, one is calcified
plaque. Uh, good in this context. Two is
mostly calcified plaque, three is mostly
non-calcified plaque, and four is
largely non-calcified plaque, the soft
plaque that we've been trying to avoid.
If uh you're looking for a deeper
explanation on what uh to look for here,
you've got the wrong guy. I too have no
idea what we're looking at here, aside
from what I just outlined. But if we
focus in on the data, we see a
statistically significant effect
indicated by a p value below 0.05 for
the omega-3 group. Those individuals
have lower Gcore around 4.5 while those
not supplementing have a 7.4 four well
into that soft plaque categorization and
likely widespread. Now to be clear, both
of these indicate increased
cardiovascular risk, but relative to one
another, the omega-3 group is doing
better. In short, omega-3s are changing
the composition of the plaque that we
have in our arteries. I think this
finding is absolutely fascinating, but
it leaves me wondering exactly how it
does that, as well as if we can even
trust these results. Why can't we trust
these results? Well, I'm not going to
jump to the conclusion that we can't,
but this type of study has flaws because
it's a cohort study, meaning we're
discussing associations here. The
researchers did match participants
across groups for a number of important
factors here. Even so, this is a small
study, and the participants still didn't
get the omega-3s as an intervention. So,
an actual capsule given by the
researchers. So, there's a high chance
for misleading interpretations. As a
result, we can only say that there's an
association between omega-3 consumption
and favorable arterial plaque changes.
But we don't need to stop there because
there have been randomized control
trials performed like this one, and they
reveal two fascinating findings.
Remember, the title of the video says
quickly, which is odd when we're
discussing something like heart disease,
which takes years, if not decades, to
develop. However, this randomized
control trial only lasted an average of
5 weeks, and yet it provides some cool
data. So, this type of data is
interventional, meaning that it brings
us with much more certainty to actually
implicating omega-3s in changing our
arterial plaque. People were randomly
assigned to the omega-3 group or the
control group given a placebo or a third
condition given sunflower oil. Then they
measured the plaque in the arteries and
they didn't just classify the plaques
based on the calcification and so on
like in the last study. They looked at
the composition of that plaque. Remember
arterial plaque is filled with
cholesterol molecules, fat molecules,
and even proteins. But it's also filled
with something else that makes it more
or less dangerous. We'll come back to
that in just a minute. For now, I'm
going to scare you with the data. Yeah,
it's a lot. And instead of straining
your eyes and boring you, I'll just
point out this one line across the
board. This is an omega-3 fat. And these
data tell us that this omega-3 is
enriched in the arterial plaque when
people consume more omega-3s. That part
is pretty self-explanatory. The more you
eat, the more you could have
incorporated into the plaque. But what
is it doing there? Well, my friend,
that's where we get to look at another
table. But before you groan and say, "I
didn't sign up to this to look at
numbers, you nerd." I'll promise to make
this extremely simple by bringing in
some images to explain the happenings.
Here's the table. And here we're looking
at the three conditions up top. I just
realized I didn't explain that in the
last table. Sorry about that. But we
have three different comparisons.
difference between sunflower oil and
control, which we don't care about in
this story. Then fish oil versus
control, we care. And fish oil versus
sunflower oil, we kind of care about
that, too. Then there's two groups of
cells found inside the plaque. That's
right, cells inside the plaque of your
arteries. They're macrofasages and TE-C
cells. Both of these cells come from
different families. One is part of your
normal defense system called the innate
immune system and the other the tea
cells come from a more specialized
immune system called the adaptive. The
big point being that they are different
immune cells. Then we have three
categories of staining. So 0 1 and two.
And the zero score stands for no
staining detected. Therefore no immune
cells present. The one indicates
moderate staining. So some immune cells
are there. And the two is the heavy
staining indicating the greatest number
of immune cells. By the way, by staining
I mean this we're using fluorescent
proteins that attach to these immune
cells specifically allowing us to
identify them. Okay, that explained. If
the number goes down like here, that
means there's less staining. And if they
go up over 1.0, that typically indicates
more of that staining group. This is all
then confirmed by the statistics the p
values which should be below 0.05 to
indicate an identified effect. So in
short there are no differences for tea
cells across any of the groups and there
are reductions in the group two staining
for the macrofasages in both omega-3
comparisons. In addition, there's more
of group one staining for the same
groups. That suggests to me that the
number of macrofasages in the plaque is
reducing although not completely
disappearing. That all matters because
macrofasages are abundant in the plaque
and they accentuate the inflammatory
response inside the plaque exacerbating
the problems coming from plaque. More
specifically, they're usually involved
in unstable forms of plaque and increase
the risk of rupture. This could be a
mechanism by which omega-3s help the
plaque stability by removing these cells
that destabilize the plaque. How
freaking cool is that? In fact, we see
that further evidenced in other data
that I won't plague you with, but it
shows that more unstable plaques have
fewer macrofasages in them, which also
associates with omega-3 levels in the
plaque. There's more that we need to get
into, including what this means for you
and how to contextualize this because
there's some nuances to be aware of, but
this is actually a pretty bare bones
analysis considering there's more data
on everything that we just went over, as
well as a brand new study on omega-3's
ability to reverse plaque in our
arteries and the differences between
omega-3 types. I'm covering all of that
in the full analysis included with the
Physionic Insiders, which also includes
access to all my analyses in article and
video format, a private podcast, a
private community that I'm highly
engaged in, and even live sessions with
me and the rest of the insider
community. And there's more, but I've
been talking about this for too long.
So, if you're interested, check out the
description and join the Physionic
Insiders. I hope to see you there. Now,
to context. We've covered two studies
and this third corroborates a lot of
what we just went over and we did
include a randomized control trial which
is important and impressive considering
the results. However, even so, it should
be noted that we could really use some
longerterm studies and just more
evidence as a whole. But that context
applied, we also have multiple
intervention studies that indicate
omega-3s are generally beneficial for
heart health by reducing heart disease
related events. So although that doesn't
speak to these specific artery effects,
it speaks to the overall trend of
omega-3 fats improving cardiovascular
health. So where does that leave us?
Well, one quick thing that I need to get
off my chest. Why don't fish do well in
school?
Because they work below sea level.
This has been entirely too serious of a
video, so I had to throw one in there.
Okay, on to the takeaways. I think
overall consuming omega-3 fats have weak
to moderate evidence indicating one of
the ways that they improve our
cardiovascular health is by remodeling
the plaque in our arteries to be less
inflamed and to be more stable. This
paired with outcome data offers evidence
that we should be consuming omega-3s. If
that's through algae, fish, krill oil,
or by eating fatty fish. See, the joke
was related. You know what else is
related? This Omega-3 video right here.
Thanks for hanging out with me and I'll
see you over there.